Register of the Socialist Workers Party Records, 1928-2002
Wisconsin Historical Society
- Part 1 (Micro 596, Micro 816, Micro 993, Micro 1078, Micro 2015, Micro 2050, AC 588, CB 131): Original Collection, 1928-1993, Micro 596; 185 reels of microfilm (35mm) and 2 films
  The documentation varies widely in content and extent, and it cannot be easily characterized either by subject or by function. Within each year, the records are arranged alphabetically by organizational name and, when necessary, by document type. As originally received from the party, the earliest files in the Chronological File partially duplicated material in the James Cannon Papers and previously-filmed portions of File 2 (primarily material on reels 32 and 33). When possible, new duplicate material was removed from File 1 before filming.
  The early files do not represent an organic recordkeeping system and there is some evidence that they have been sorted and reorganized repeatedly. Items photocopied from other archival collections are occasionally included as well. For example, many of the 1937 letters from Harry Milton to Martin Abern are copies from the Albert Glotzer collection. (This provenance has been indicated on the film by microfilming the Glotzer stamp on the back of each photocopied document.) Still other material has clearly been copied from the J.B.S. Hardman collection at the Tamiment Library. Unfortunately, the source of other photocopied material has not been indicated, and, as a result, researchers wishing to publish material from the HISTORICAL FILES are advised to confirm the original or photocopied nature of the paper files in the SHSW archives.
  Because these documents have lost their original context and because many were undated, the final arrangement of parts of File 1 must be considered tentative.
  The earliest material is quite fragmentary, including publications such as a 1925 document, Red International of Labor Unions, and a bulletin issued in 1928 by the Konikow Group. Publications issued by organizations not connected to the SWP have been separated to the SHSW Library. There is little about the Communist Party here, except for a mimeographed version of some speeches by Stalin and a letter from the Comintern addressed to the American Communist Party.
  There are also miscellaneous files of documents about the various organizations which preceded the Socialist Workers Party including correspondence, leaflets, mimeographed branch circulars, policy statements, etc. (Publications of these groups have generally been filmed with the Publications series.) Some documents here are of uncertain provenance. The Conference for Progressive Labor Action, for example, is represented by a file of Sam Sponseller, Ted Selander, and other Toledo activists. This file includes a large quantity of form letters written by A.J. Muste as well as information on Lucas County labor conditions. The same provenance is evident in the file on the American Workers Party, the successor to the CPLA, although this file also incorporates material from the collection at the Tamiment Library of J.B.S. Hardman, an AWP leader. The Workers Party, which was formed by the merger of CLA and AWP, is represented by a large quantity of leaflets, form letters, and other information distributed to the membership. Also included are 1935 minutes of the party's Harlem branch. The file on the Non-Partisan Labor Defense may have been photocopied from the Herbert Solow Papers. It largely concerns operations in California. The chronological file contains only limited documentation relating to the Socialist Party, primarily a heterogeneous group of papers relating to the Trotskyists' sojourn in the SP in 1937. Also present is a file--apparently from a California branch--of correspondence to and from Cannon. There is also only scant material about Trotskyist offshots such as the Revolutionary Workers Party (the Oehlerites).
  Like the early material in the chronological file, much of the post-1938 documentation consists of mimeographed material that was widely circulated. Notable is the mimeographed correspondence and positions on the 1939-1940 Russian Discussion which resulted in the departure of Max Shachtman and his followers.
  Tour reports are a predominant element throughout the series, as is correspondence on the regroupment efforts of the 1950s. The tour files include detailed narrative and statistical reports from SWP representatives such as Grace Carlson, George Clarke, Linda Jenness, Myra Tanner Weiss, and John G. Usick Wright about conditions in the branches. The regroupment material contains detailed letters to Dobbs and Kerry about branch relations with Stalinists during the mid 1950s. A second file, primarily made up of correspondence and documents of George Stryker of Bayport, New York (why this file was in the National Office records is not known), relates to the American Forum for Socialist Education, an attempt by A.J. Muste to unite various elements of the American Left. (Muste, as well as Norman Thomas and David McReynolds are represented in the correspondence here.) Related to this is the file on the United Independent-Socialist Campaign Committee in New York in 1958. More internal in focus is the material on Tim Wohlforth and the younger membership of the SWP and on the fundraising committee formed in the early 1960s.
  Other disparate files of research interest include information on the party's campaign against Gerald L. K. Smith during World War II; harassment experienced during the late 1960s from the Legion of Justice, a right wing Chicago-area organization; and the Student Committee for Travel to Cuba. There are also reports submitted to Charles Carsten about post-World War II organizing by the SWP among veterans. Another file documenting the party's curious relationship with Lyndon LaRouche, Jr., contains many writings by LaRouche and information on the harassment experienced by the SWP (and by David McReynolds) from LaRouche's National Caucus of Labor Committees. A small file on the Kennedy assassination includes a printed copy of Dobbs' Warren Commission testimony, memoranda, and copies of the SWP documents that were presented in evidence during the investigation.
  The majority of File 2, the Organizational File, was originally part of two older microfilm editions of the records of the SWP. This film included documents which were unavailable for later refilming, and which therefore have been preserved by retaining the relevant sections of the older film. Unlike more recent filming done at SHSW these records were filmed without counter numbers and as a result some groups of records are accessed solely by a reel segment number. (Some records from the older microfilm that pertained to the Fourth International, the Socialist Party-Social Democratic Federation, and various organizations of socialist young people were recataloged as Socialist Records, Micro 684.)
  The file now consists of documents about various predecessors of the Socialist Workers Party (such as the Communist League of America, the Workers Party, and the Young People's Socialist League) and various Trotskyist opponents, splinters, and tendencies. The records consist almost exclusively of printed bulletins but they differ reflecting the size and activity of the groups in questions. The records of the first three groups, all of which emerged from predecessors of the SWP, are sparse. They are the League for a Revolutionary Workers Party (Fieldites), a very small Trotskyist group which was formed in 1934 and led by B.J. Field; the ultra-left Communist League of Struggle (Weisbordites), a small group led by Albert Weisbord which existed from 1932 to 1937; and the Revolutionary Workers League (Oehlerites), a relatively large Trotskyist group founded in 1936 in opposition to the entrance of the WP into the SP. In addition, this series contains a variety of documents produced by the Johnson-Forest Tendency, a group which separated from the SWP in 1941. Under the leadership of C.L.R. James, it existed independently except for brief periods. The Johnson-Forest Tendency records, dating from 1942 to 1947, include internal materials; a long tract, The Invading Socialist Society; and Internal Bulletins issued during 1947. Finally, the series includes a significant body of records produced by the second Workers Party from 1943 to 1957. The files are comprised almost entirely of WP internal discussion bulletins and of a similar bulletin, the Forum, of its successor group, the Independent Socialist League.
  Opponents Files
  The alphabetically-arranged Opponents Files consist of information about groups on the radical left that the SWP itself characterized as opponents. This series differs from File 2 of the HISTORICAL FILES primarily in that File 2 contains information on early opponents, while this series represents later opposition groups. More precisely the file contains information about the membership and intentions of the Communist Party and various CP splinter groups, as well as a few files on SWP splinters such as the Committee for a Revolutionary Socialist Party, the Spartacist League, and the small publication Spark. Except for the files on CPUSA the documentation primarily dates from the 1970s and 1980s. Although no internal evidence ties the information to him, it is thought that this material may be the Tom Kerry reference files on the CP which are referred to in the Historical Society's background correspondence with the SWP.
  The information on the CP spans the period from the 1930s to the 1970s and it primarily consists of leaflets, flyers, and correspondence. (Organizational newsletters and publications files have been separated to the SHSW Library.) Although the information is disparate in nature, the files on the 1966 and 1969 national conventions contain a large quantity of focused documentation: primarily resolutions and distributions. Also useful is the file of educational and discussion materials issued by CPUSA during the 1940s. An isolated item of special note is a 1934 financial balance sheet.
  The remainder of the files in the opponents section are comparatively small, often consisting of a few pieces of correspondence to SWP national office staff about the group in question and a few distributions and leaflets. Again the correspondence mixes letters to and from YSA staff with letters to and from SWP leaders. Sometimes there are mimeographed memoranda from the SWP and the YSA to national committee members.
  Notable organizational files are those on the DuBois Club, which includes a large quantity of material distributed at the founding convention in June 1964. The files also document extensive monitoring of the Young Workers Liberation League by the SWP-YSA. Information on the National Alliance Against Racism and Political Repression includes mailings that document its emergence from the CP's Angela Davis defense committee. A substantial number of letters and memoranda also track the Trotskyists' response to the Maoist Revolutionary Communist Party and its youth arms, the Revolutionary Communist Youth Brigade and the Revolutionary Student Brigade. The file on the Sparticist League contains ample documentation of the anti-SWP campaign waged by the league.
  Other material which warrants mention is a file of general reports, mainly 1970-1976, from chapters around the country regarding the activities of their local opponents. Also notable is a clipping scrapbook about the role of the American Labor Party and the SWP in New York City elections in 1949.
  Internal Discussions and Disputes
  The Internal Discussions and Disputes series highlights several issues of party loyalty and policy that divided the party. The files are ordered alphabetically by the name applied by the SWP in organizing the files, and they range in date from the early 1950s to the late 1980s. The files address many of the same questions about party discipline and internal factionalism documented in the Control Commission files, and it is difficult to tell how the two sections are related.
  Although the SWP has a long history of internal factionalism and the party itself was founded as a result of an ideological split within the Communist Party, such internecine conflicts seemed to escalate in the 1970s and 1980s when a new generation took control of party leadership. Many of these files indicate that policy of the SWP toward leftist movements around the world was often the catalyst for internal divison. In particular, the Internationalist Tendency, the Leninist Faction, and the Socialist Action files reveal that key party members, including Arne Swabeck, were unhappy with SWP policy toward China, Argentina, Central America, and Chile after the 1960s and that they believed the new leadership was abandoning the principles of Leninism. The Appeals and Resignations file contains particularly interesting and useful documentation about party members who criticized the party in the late 1970s.
  While these files trace the evolution of party factionalism over the question of internationalism, they also demonstrate that the debate over international policy fueled a more general discussion about factions and the proper definitions of indiscipline and disloyalty in the SWP. On the whole, the Internal Discussion and Disputes files portray a party struggling to reconcile the revolutionary ideas of the old guard with the realities faced by the new members.
  - Administrative Records
    - Constitutions
      - 1935-1971, Micro 816 (Reel 35, Frame 1)
      - 1975, 1977, Micro 993 (Reel 49, Frame 1)
      - 1981, 1984, Micro 1078 (Reel 60, Frame 1)
      - 1988, Micro 2015 (Reel 74, Frame 1)
    - Minutes
      - Political Committee/National Committee/and National Conventions combined
        - 1940, Micro 596 (Reel 1, Frame 593)
        - 1941-1944 (Reel 2)
        - 1945-1946 (Reel 3)
        - 1947-1948 (Reel 4)
          - 1948 convention: filmed footage, AC 588
        - 1949-1951, Micro 596 (Reel 5)
        - 1952-1953, July (Reel 6)
        - 1953, August - 1954, June (Reel 7)
        - 1954, July - 1956 (Reel 8)
        - 1957-1959, May (Reel 9)
        - 1959, June - 1961 (Reel 10)
        - 1962-1964 (Reel 11)
        - 1965-1967, August (Reel 12)
        - 1967, September - 1969, June (Reel 13)
        - 1969, July - 1970 (Reel 14, Frame 1)
        - 1971, Micro 816 (Reel 35, Frame 172)
        - 1972-1973, October (Reel 36, Frame 1)
        - 1973, October - 1975, April (Reel 37, Frame 1)
        - 1975, May - December (Reel 38, Frame 1)
        - 1976, Micro 993 (Reel 49, Frame 14)
        - 1977-1978 (Reel 50)
        - 1979-1980, June (Reel 51)
        - 1980, July - December (Reel 52, Frame 1)
        - 1981, Micro 1078 (Reel 60, Frame 12)
        - 1982
          - January-February (Reel 61, Frame 1)
          - March-April (Reel 62, Frame 1)
          - May-August (Reel 61, Frame 238)
          - September-December (Reel 62, Frame 346)
        - 1983
          - January-April (Reel 62, Frame 672)
          - May-August (Reel 63, Frame 1)
          - September-December (Reel 64, Frame 1)
        - 1984
          - January-April (Reel 64, Frame 590)
          - May-September (Reel 65, Frame 1)
          - October-December (Reel 66, Frame 1)
        - 1985
          - January-May (Reel 66, Frame 336)
          - June-December (Reel 67, Frame 1)
        - 1986, Micro 2015 (Reel 72, Frame 1)
        - 1987 (Reel 73, Frame 1)
        - 1988 (Reel 74, Frame 1)
        - 1989 (Reel 75)
        - 1990
          - January-June, Meetings 1-66 (Reel 77)
          - July-December, Meetings 67-130 (Reel 78, Frame 780)
        - 1991
          - January-June, Meetings 1-66 (Reel 80)
          - July-December, Meetings 67-134 (Reel 81)
        - 1992, Micro 2050
          - January-April, Meetings 1-38 (Reel 57, Frame 4)
          - May-July 13, Meetings 39-72 (Reel 58)
          - July 15-September, Meetings 73-100 (Reel 59)
          - October-December, Meetings 101-125 (Reel 60)
        - 1993
          - January-March, Meetings 1-38 (Reel 61, Frame 531)
          - April-July, Meetings 39-80 (Reel 62)
          - August-December, Meetings 81-122 (Reel 63, Frame 1)
          - Mailings to National Committee and index (Reel 63, Frame 740)
      - Leadership Committee minutes
        - Administrative Committee, 1981-1985 (Reel 63A)
        - Organization Bureau (Committee)
          - 1979-1985 (Reel 64, Frame 1)
          - 1986-1988 (Reel 65, Frame 3)
        - Organization and Trade Union Bureau, 1987-1988 (Reel 65, Frame 695)
        - Political Bureau
          - 1982-1984 (Reel 66, Frame 1)
          - 1992, September - October 17 (Reel 67, Frame 1)
          - 1992, October 23 - November (Reel 68, Frame 1)
        - Secretariat, 1978, 1982-1984 (Reel 69, Frame 1)
        - Trade Union Bureau (Committee), 1977-1987 (Reel 69, Frame 653)
        - Women's Liberation Steering Committee, 1983-1984 (Reel 70, Frame 2)
    - Control Commission records
      - History (Reel 71, Frame 3)
      - Cases
        - Austin, Rudie, 1969-1971 (Reel 71, Frame 78)
        - Bennett (Beidel), Lydia, 1945 (Reel 71, Frame 227)
        - Bryant, Paul, 1945-1946 (Reel 71, Frame 260)
        - Caldwell, Sylvia (Comrade S), 1947-1977 (Reel 71, Frame 432)
        - Carroll, Elaine, 1967-1974 (Reel 71, Frame 530)
        - Dennis ?, 1942 (Reel 71, Frame 540)
        - Dominican split, 1979-1980 (Reel 71, Frame 553)
        - Duncan, Al, 1966-1977 (Reel 71, Frame 683)
        - Evans, Les, 1970, 1981-1982 (Reel 71, Frame 721)
        - Hannaford, Bruce, 1977 (Reel 71, Frame 853)
        - Hatch, Aron Harris Freedman, 1980, 1993 (Reel 71, Frame 862)
        - Heisler, Ed, 1962-1963 (Reel 71, Frame 890)
        - Houston violence, 1979-1980, 1993 (Reel 72, Frame 3)
        - IEC to members outside leadership, 1977-1981 (Reel 72, Frame 196)
        - Jeffries, Dave, 1946 (Reel 72, Frame 355)
        - Jensen, Paul, 1948-1949 (Reel 72, Frame 367)
        - Leonard, Debby, 1975-1976 (Reel 72, Frame 426)
        - Lewin, Herb, 1943-1944 (Reel 72, Frame 461)
        - MacFarland, Red, 1943 (Reel 72, Frame 485)
        - McRae, Leroy, 1964-1965 (Reel 72, Frame 497)
        - Masheer, Fardem, 1976-1977 (Reel 72, Frame 607)
        - Miller ?, 1943 (Reel 72, Frame 636)
        - Minneapolis, 1947 (Reel 72, Frame 645)
        - Minority faction, 1946-1947 (Reel 72, Frame 662)
        - Miscellaneous cases, 1946 (Reel 72, Frame 690)
        - Morrow-Goldman dispute, 1946 (Reel 72, Frame 699)
        - Patrick, John, 1940-1941 (Reel 72, Frame 722)
        - Reiner, Sylvia et al., 1944 (Reel 72, Frame 869)
        - Reid, Willie, 1959 (Reel 72, Frame 914)
        - Roy ?, 1944 (Reel 72, Frame 922)
        - Smith, Joe, 1946-1948 (Reel 72, Frame 928)
        - Special investigations, 1938-1941 (Reel 72, Frame 991)
    - Circular letters
      - 1938-1939 (Reel 73, Frame 2)
      - 1940-1944, Micro 596 (Reel 27, Frame 276)
      - 1945-1951 (Reel 28, Frame 1)
      - 1952-1964 (Reel 29, Frame 1)
      - 1965-1970 (Reel 30, Frame 1)
      - 1971-1972, January, Micro 816 (Reel 38, Frame 433)
      - 1972, July - 1974 (Reel 39, Frame 1)
      - 1975 (Reel 40, Frame 1)
      - 1976, Micro 993 (Reel 52, Frame 520)
      - 1977 (Reel 53)
      - 1978-1979 (Reel 54)
      - 1980 (Reel 55)
      - 1981 January - February, Micro 1078 (Reel 67, Frame 734)
      - 1981 March - 1983 (Reel 68, Frame 1)
      - 1984-1985 (Reel 69)
      - 1986, Micro 2015 (Reel 72, Frame 649)
      - 1987 (Reel 73, Frame 481)
      - 1988 (Reel 74, Frame 669)
      - 1989 (Reel 76, Frame 1)
      - 1990 (Reel 79, Frame 1)
      - 1991 (Reel 82, Frame 1)
      - 1992, Micro 2050
        - January-September (Reel 73, Frame 273)
        - October-December (Reel 74, Frame 1)
      - 1993 (Reel 74, Frame 215)
    - Membership statistics and miscellaneous administrative records
      - Membership statistics, 1938, 1940-1989 (Reel 75, Frame 1)
      - Financial recordkeeping handbook, 1978 (Reel 75, Frame 409)
  - Publication Records
    - Background and governance
      - Historical correspondence regarding Pioneer and Merit, 1963-1966, undated
        - Establishment of Merit (Reel 87, Frame 1)
        - International Socialist Review bylaws, 1968 (Reel 87, Frame 55)
        - Militant, bylaws and statements of ownership, 1958-1989, undated (Reel 87, Frame 58)
        - Perspectiva Mundial, 1977-1978 (Reel 87, Frame 91)
        - Minutes of governing committees
          - Editorial Committee, 1971-1975 (Reel 87, Frame 112)
          - Executive Committee, 1974-1975 (Reel 87, Frame 241)
          - Promotion Committee, 1973-1974 (Reel 87, Frame 290)
          - Publications Committee, 1947, 1967-1971 (Reel 87, Frame 323)
      - Administrative documents
        - Merit Publishers: Catalog and financial statements, 1965-1966 (Reel 87, Frame 487)
        - Militant: Correspondence, 1940-1951, 1964 (Reel 87, Frame 505)
      - Sales reports and comparisons
        - 1940-1990 (Reel 87, Frame 682)
        - Pathfinder Press
          - Book covers (Reel 87, Frame 784)
          - Catalogs, 1970-1992 (Reel 88, Frame 1)
          - Order forms, 1960s-1992 (Reel 88, Frame 358)
          - Promotional material, undated (Reel 88, Frame 482)
          - Sales statistics
            - General, 1971-1987 (Reel 88, Frame 714)
            - Maurice Bishop Speaks, 1984 (Reel 88, Frame 802)
      - Pioneer Publishers
        - Catalogs, 1935-1965, undated (Reel 89, Frame 1)
        - Correspondence, 1930?-1966 (Reel 89, Frame 156)
        - Narrative reports, 1940-1968 (Reel 89, Frame 242)
        - Sales reports, 1940-1948, 1954-1963 (Reel 89, Frame 330)
    - Miscellany
      - Ernest Mandel publishing correspondence, 1962-1965 (Reel 89, Frame 444)
      - Socialist Workers Party News Releases, 1945-1966, undated (Reel 89, Frame 489)
      - Speakers Bureau
        - Correspondence, reports, 1972-1977 (Reel 89, Frame 604)
        - Viewpoint brochures, 1972-1976 (Reel 89, Frame 934)
      - Trotsky publishing project, 1971, 1975 (Reel 89, Frame 1007)
    - Library
      - Bulletin contents inventory, undated, Micro 596 (Reel 15, Frame 446A)
      - Activist Panels
        - Volume I, 1970 (Reel 31, Frame 552)
        - Duplicate, Micro 816 (Reel 48, Frame 296)
      - Appeal Army, 1939, Micro 2050 (Reel 89, Frame 1002)
      - Discussion Bulletin, SWP, Micro 596
        - 1950, Numbers 1-5 (Reel 18, Frame 230)
        - 1951, Numbers 6-9 (Reel 18, Frame 450)
        - 1953-1955, Numbers 11-33 (Reel 19, Frame 36)
        - 1956-1959 (Reel 20, Frame 55)
        - 1959-1962 (Reel 21)
        - 1962-1963, Volume XXIII, Number 6-Volume XXIV, Number 28 (Reel 22)
        - 1963, Volume XXIV, Numbers 29-34 (Reel 23, Frame 1)
        - 1965, Volume XXV, Numbers 1-16 (Reel 23, Frame 387)
        - 1967, Volume XXVI, Numbers 1-12 (Reel 24, Frame 88)
        - 1969, Volume XXVII, Numbers 1-13 (Reel 24, Frame 469)
        - 1970-1971, Volume XXVIII-XXIX, Micro 816 (Reel 43, Frame 393)
        - 1972-1973, Volume XXX-XXXII (Reel 44)
        - 1975, Volume XXXIII (Reel 45, Frame 1)
        - 1976-1979, Volume XXXV, Number 1-XXVI, Number 13, Micro 993; Not published in 1978. (Reel 58)
        - 1979, Volume XXXVI, Numbers 14-27, No 1980. (Reel 59, Frame 1)
        - 1981, 1984-1985, Volume XXXVII-Volume XXXX, Micro 1078 (Reel 71, Frame 1)
        - 1988, Volume XXXXI, Numbers 1-8, Micro 2015 (Reel 74, Frame 958)
        - 1990, Volume XXXXII, Numbers 1-42 (Reel 79, Frame 586)
        - 1991, Volume XXXXIII, Numbers 1-5 (Reel 82, Frame 650)
      - Education for Socialists, Micro 816
        - 1943 (Reel 45, Frame 285)
        - 1966-1967 (Reel 45, Frame 666)
        - 1968-1972 (Reel 46, Frame 321)
        - 1973-1975 (Reel 47, Frame 1)
        - 1976-1982, July, Micro 2050 (Reel 90, Frame 1)